Guide to the Christian Barthelmess Photograph Album and Photographs of Montana, New Mexico, and Colorado
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Photograph album and photographs of Montana, New Mexico, and Colorado.
1881-1903
WA Photos 404
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.79
Photographs created by Christian Barthelmess of people and places in New Mexico, Colorado, and Montana, 1881-1903.
Barthelmess, Christian, 1854-1906
General note
Title devised by cataloger.
General note
Some images in the album have duplicate photographic prints in the collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Andrew Smith Gallery on the Arthur Corbitt Hoskins Memorial Fund, 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biography
Originally from Bavaria, Christian Barthelmess served in the United States Army during the Indian Wars and the Spanish American War as a musician and photographer, 1876-1903.
Scope and Contents
Seventy-six photographs, consisting of fifty photographic prints in an album and twenty-six loose photographic prints, created by Christian Barthelmess of people and places in New Mexico, Colorado, and Montana, 1881-1903.
Arrangement
Photographic prints are arranged georgraphically.
Apache Indians -- Pictorial works; Badlands -- Montana -- Pictorial works; Bands (Music) -- Pictorial works; Cheyenne Indians -- Pictorial works; Fort Lewis (Colo.) -- Pictorial works; Indians of North America -- Pictorial works; Tiwa Indians -- Pictorial works; White Mountain Apache Indians -- Pictorial works; Zuni Indians -- Pictorial works; Arizona -- Pictorial works; Colorado -- Pictorial works; Dowa Yalanne (McKinley County, N.M.) -- Pictorial works; Emerald, Lake (Colo.) -- Pictorial works; Fort Keogh (Mont.) -- Pictorial works; Fort Wingate (N.M.) -- Pictorial works; La Plata River (Colo. and N.M.) -- Pictorial works; Lame Deer (Mont.) -- Pictorial works; Little Bighorn Battlefield (Mont.) -- Pictorial works; Montana -- Pictorial works; New Mexico -- Pictorial works; Parrot (Colo.) -- Pictorial works; Perilla Mountains (Ariz.) -- Pictorial works; Santa Fe (N.M.) -- Pictorial works; Zuni (N.M.) -- Pictorial works; Photograph albums; Photographic prints; Two Moons, b. 1839? -- Pictorial works; Barthelmess, Christian, 1854-1906; Casey, Edward W. -- Pictorial works; Jones, Frank B. -- Pictorial works; Kell, William H. -- Pictorial works; Miles, Nelson Appleton, 1839-1925 -- Pictorial works; Miner, Charles W. -- Pictorial works; Ritner, Isaac Newton -- Pictorial works; Smith, Allen, b. 1849 -- Pictorial works; Swaine, Cornelia -- Pictorial works; Swaine, Peter Tyler -- Pictorial works; Swaine, William -- Pictorial works; United States. Army. Cavalry, 4th -- Pictorial works; United States. Army. Cavalry, 6th -- Pictorial works; United States. Army. Infantry, 22nd -- Pictorial works; Santa Fe Tertio-Millennial Celebration and Exposition ( 1883 Santa Fe, N.M.)
- Photographic Prints, 1888-1906; Series I; Unmounted photographic prints except where noted.; (26 photographic prints)
  Arrangement
  Series arranged geographically.
  Scope and Contents
  Loose photographic prints of locations in Montana and New Mexico.
  General note
  Descriptions of the photographic prints are provided by the archivist.
  - Fort Keogh, Montana
    - View looking northwest of officers quarters on Southern Avenue, Fort Keogh, Montana, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Exterior portraits
      - Private in the Twenty-Second infantry, Company C, in a wheelchair and three hospital corpsmen, 1888-1898 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Includes a hospital steward with a moustache on the left of the man in the wheelchair and a clean-shaven acting hospital steward on the extreme right, the other standing man is a private
      - Private in the Twenty-Second infantry, Company C, in a wheelchair and six hospital corpsmen, 1888-1898 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Includes the hospital steward with a moustache on the left of the man in the wheelchair and a clean-shaven acting hospital steward on the extreme right, the other four men are privates
      - Two officers, nine women, three girls, and two dogs on an ice rink established in front of the quarters of the commander, 1888-1898 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Several women and children wear ice skates
      - Four officers, five civilian men, three women, and a dog posed standing and sitting in front of an ivy covered building, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Probably officers from the the Twenty-Second Infantry and Tenth Cavalry. Man seated and looking to the right is identified as Chaplin Isaac Newton Ritner
      - Group of officers, civilian men, and women, in front of the quarters of the commander, 1888-1898 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
      - Two men and two women in a fenced yard, probably a yard of a married enlisted mens quarters located east of the garrison surrounding the parade field called "Soapsuds Row", 1888-1898 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        A woman also holds a cat
  - Fort Keogh, Montana (Vicinity)
    - Rocky landscape near a river, probably the badlands of eastern Montana along the Yellowstone River, 1888-1898 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Rocky landscape, probably the badlands of eastern Montana, 1888-1898 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Column of troops led by members of the Second Infantry Band with their instruments in cases, and a corporal with a bicycle on the right of the image, near the Tongue River, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - A first lieutenant in the Fourth Regiment of the United States Cavalry demonstrating horse training techniques, circa 1902-1906 (Box 1, Folder 12-15)
    - Seven men, three women, and two children, which includes a Native American man and woman, posed standing in front of a building, possibly at an Indian Agency, 1888-1889; Cabinet photograph (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Group portrait of primarily Native Americans, consisting seven children, ten women, and fourteen men, including one white man, 1888-1889; Boudoir photograph (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Incorrect inscription on verso
    - Four women posed sitting in a buck wagon pulled by two horses on a snow-covered landscape, 1888-1898 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Five women posed sitting in a buck wagon pulled by a single horse, 1888-1898 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Studio portrait of a young Cheyenne Indian woman, 1890-1896 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Lame Deer Agency, Montana
    - Group of Native American and white men under porch of a log building, 1889; Boudoir photograph (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Identified as General Nelson A. Miles in council with Cheyenne Chiefs. Miles is posed sitting at a table, Two Moons is posed sitting and wearing a white shirt and Army Lieutenant Edward W. Casey immediately behind him
  - Little Bighorn River, Montana
    - Stone obelisk monument to officers and soldiers killed in the Battle of Little Big Horn, 1888-1898 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Fort Wingate, New Mexico
    - Thirty-eight soldiers and two dogs in a courtyard with snow on the ground among brick buildings, probably barracks, 1881-1884; Imperial photograph (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Fort Wingate, New Mexico (Vicinity)
    - Cavalry soldier mounted on horseback, 1881-1884; Imperial photograph (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Identified as possibly Capitan Allen Smith, although his uniform shows first sergeant chevrons
    - Four Navajo Indian men and a white soldier, 1881-1884; Imperial photograph (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Identified as possibly Capitan Allen Smith, although his uniform shows first sergeant chevrons, with Navajo scouts
    - Nine soldiers and a herd of horses at a spring, 1881-1884 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Album, 1881-1889; Series II; 50 photographic prints mounted in an album
  Described in the original order of the album
  Images include locations in Colorado, Montana, New Mexico, and Arizona. Many of the photographs include manuscript inscriptions in German deutscher Schrift. A few images have duplicates in the album.
  - Native American woman, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Location of image: Fort Wingate, New Mexico
    Identified as Tanapa, daughter of Mariana
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Eine Navajo Squaw in National costüm
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: A Navajo Squaw in national costume
  - Zuni mountain sheep dance, 1882, Apr 21 (Box 2)
    Location of image: Zuni Pueblo, New Mexico
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Ein Tanz d. Berschäfer (Zuni Indianer) Zuni ist eine Stadt der pueblos u. Die einzip ubrig gebliebene von 5 von den alten [indeciperable] [indeciperable] Städten Cibolas
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: A dance of the mountain shepherd (Zuni Indian). Zuni is a city of the Pueblos and the fifth and only remaining city of the old [indeciperable] [indeciperable] cities Cibolas
  - Native American boy, age fifteen years, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Navajo 15 Jahr alten Knabe
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Navajo 15 year old boy
  - Three men, two women, and a boy posed sitting and fishing in a mountain stream, 1887-1888 (Box 2)
    Location of image: Fort Lewis, Colorado (Vicinity)
    Identified as Colonel Peter Tyler Swaine sitting in the upper center with his wife, Cornelia Swaine, above his son, William Swaine, and Captain William Conway and his wife; the other man is unidentified
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Ein Fischerausflug von Officiere u. ihren Damen an einem Gebirgsfluss in Colorado
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: A fishing expedition of officers and their ladies at a mountain river in Colorado
  - Home of the commander of Fort Keogh, 1888-1889 (Box 2)
    Location of image: Fort Keogh, Montana
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Das Haus des Commandanten von Fort Koegh
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: The house of the commander of Fort Koegh
  - Dancers from the Picuris Pueblo during the Tertio-Millenial Anniversary Celebration and Grand Mining and Industrial Exposition, 1883, Jul (Box 2)
    Location of image: Santa Fe, New Mexico
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Hirschtanz der Pueblo Indianer
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Deer dance of the Pueblo Indians
  - Studio portrait of an elderly Native American woman, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Washie, Navajo Squaw, 105 Jahre alt
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Washie, Navajo Squaw, 105 years old
  - Santa Fe, New Mexico, with the Palace Hotel prominently on the right of the image, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Santa Fe (Colorado)
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Santa Fe (Colorado)
  - Hospital in Fort Keogh, 1888-1889 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Hospital in Fort Keogh
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Hospital in Fort Keogh
  - Four Navajo Indian men and a white soldier, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Identified as Capitan Allen Smith with Navajo scouts
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Navajo Kundschafter
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Navajo scouts
  - Waterfall on the La Plata River near Parrot, Colorado, with fifteen men, women, and children on the rocky bank, 1887-1888 (Box 2)
    Location of image: Parrot, Colorado (Vicinity)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Wasserfall des La Plata, Col.
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Waterfall of the La Plata (Colorado)
  - Eleven cavalry soldiers in camp, 1888-1889 (Box 2)
    Location of image: Yellow River, Montana
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: 1. Troup I Cav. U.S.A. im Camp am Yellow Flusse [undeciphered abbreviation] Fort Koegh
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Troop of the 1st Cavalry Regiment in camp on the Yellow River near Fort Koegh
  - Cheyenne Indian scouts with Lieutenant Edward Casey, who is posed sitting in the center of the rear row., 1889 (Box 2)
    Location of image: Fort Keogh, Montana (Vicinity)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Cheyenne Kundschafter im Camp
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Cheyenne scouts in the Camp
  - Waterfall on the La Plata River near Parrot, Colorado, with twelve men, women, and children on the rocky bank, 1887-1888 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Fall des La Plata
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Fall of the La Plata
  - Two Navajo Indian women at a weaving loom weaving jackets with a Navajo Indian child between them, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Navajo Frauen beim Jacken weben
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Navajo women weaving jackets
  - Studio portrait of a Navajo Indian fruit vendor with a man posed standing and holding a box of apples and a box of plums at his feet, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Ein Peublo Fruchtverkäufer
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: A Peublo fruit salesman
  - Fort Lewis, Colorado, 1887-1888 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Fort Lewis, Colorado
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Fort Lewis, Colorado
  - Studio portrait of a Navajo Indian fruit vendor with a man posed standing and holding a box of apples and a box of plums at his feet, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription:
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription:
  - Four Pueblo Indian dancers dancing with sheilds in front of a large groups of over forty Pueblo Indians., 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Location of image: New Mexico
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Adlertanz der Peublos
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Eagle dance of the Peublos
  - Detail photograph of a yucca in bloom, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Ein Yucca
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: A Yucca
  - Five men in camp in a snow-covered forest with a wagon nearby, 1887-1888 (Box 2)
    Location of image: Fort Lewis, Colorado
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Auf der Jagd eingeschneit
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: On the hunt in-snowed
  - Scouts in camp, including two Apache Indian men holding rifles and two white men, of the Sixth Cavalry, 1884-1886 (Box 2)
    Location of image: Emory Spring, Perilla Mountains, Cochise County, Arizona Territory
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Apachen [word undeciphered] in dem Sierra Madre Gebirge (Mexico)
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Apachen [ word undeciphered ] in the Sierra Madre mountains (Mexico)
  - Three men on the shore of Emerald Lake, Colorado, 1884-1886 (Box 2)
    Location of image: Emerald Lake, Colorado
    Identified as Lieutenant Kell, C. W. Miner, and Lieutenant Jones
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Erlas See
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Decree Lake
  - Two men standing and sitting on rock ledge above a cascading waterfall, 1884-1886 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Wasserfall in Colorado
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Waterfall in Colorado
  - A small and a large loom in a Navajo Indian camp, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Innere Ansicht eines Navajo Hauses
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Interior view of a Navajo house
  - Navajo Indian woman weaving on a loom, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Navajo Frau beim Jacken weben
  - Group in front of the Pony Trader's Store, a general merchandise store. The group consists of six white men, four Indian men, two Indian women, and a white girl, 1888-1889 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Das Haus des Kaufmanns in Fort Koegh
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: The merchant house at Fort Koegh
  - View looking southeast of a snow-covered landscape and officers quarters on Southern Avenue, 1888-1889 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Ein Theil der Gebäude für Officere in Fort Koegh
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Part of the building for officers at Fort Koegh
  - View of a Zuni Pueblo, New Mexico, and includes several individuals among ovens and another on the roof, 1882 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Zuni von den Häusern ausgesehen
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Zuni seen from the houses
  - Two soldiers standing among stone walls, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Location of image: Pescado, New Mexico
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Pescado ein Zuni dorf
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Pescado, a Zuni village
  - White man, an Indian man, and a horse, probably at the foot of Dowa Yalanne (also known as Corn Mountian or Taaiyalone Mountain), 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Location of image: Dowa Yalanne, New Mexico
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Tojoalana der [1 word undeciphered] der Zuni
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Taaiyalone Mountain
  - Indian man at the foot of cliffs at Dowa Yalanne (also known as Corn Mountian or Taaiyalone Mountain), 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Tojoalana der [1 word undeciphered]
  - Soldier posed sitting on the low wall of the Zuni Mission, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Ansicht von Zuni
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: View of Zuni
  - Five-mule train and a group of five Zuni Indians in a with a snow-covered landscape in front of adobe buildings, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Location of image: Nutria, New Mexico
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Neutria ein Zuni dorf
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Nutria, a Zuni village
  - Five Apache Indian men posed holding rifles, one also holding a revolver, as well as cartridge belts, 1884-1887 (Box 2)
    Location of image: Fort Bayard, New Mexico (Vicinity)
    Identified as White Mountain Apache scouts
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Apachen Kundschafter
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Apache Scouts
  - Zuni Indian woman spinning yarn, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Eine Zuni Squaw spinnend
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: A Zuni Squaw spinning
  - Zuni Indian woman weaving using a backstrap loom, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Eine Zuni Squaw webend
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: A Zuni Squaw weaving
  - Zuni Indian girl, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Mädchentypen!
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Girl types
  - Zuni Indian girls, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
  - Zuni Indian man and seven Zuni Indian children, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Zuni Familie
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Zuni Family
  - Ten soldiers in camp, identified as members of the regimental band for the 6th United States Cavalry in camp, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Hauptquartier d. Musik d. 6ten Cav. Reg. im Felde
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Regimental band for the 6th United States Cavalry in camp
  - Twenty-one soldiers in Troop A, 6th United States Cavalry in camp., 1886 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Ein Troop Cav. im Camp
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Cavalry troop in camp.
  - Forty-one soldiers from the 6th United States Cavalry in camp., 1886 (Box 2)
  - Twenty-one soldiers in Troop G, 6th United States Cavalry in camp., 1886 (Box 2)
    Location of image: Cottonwood Creek, New Mexico
  - Five men, two women, and two boy posed standing on the shore of a river or lake, 1887-1888 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Eine künstliche Forellenfischerei.Colorado
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: An artificial trout fishery, Colorado
  - Man posed sitting on a horse on a grassy shore of a lake and near a forest edge, 1887-1888 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Bergsee in Colorado
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Mountain lake in Colorado
  - Lake with exposed waterplants and a forest in the distant shore, 1887-1888 (Box 2)
  - Three men on the shore of Emerald Lake, Colorado, 1884-1886 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: II Ansicht des Erlass Sees
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Second View of Lake Erlas
  - Portrait five men, two women, and a boy, posed sitting and standing in camp, with two men holding fishing poles, 1887-1888 (Box 2)
    Identified as Colonel Peter T. Swaine posed standing and holding a fishing pole, and the boy is his son, William Swaine
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Der Commandirende in Gesellschaft auf einem Fischausfluge
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: The Company Commander on a Fishing Trip
  - Four men and a Native American boy, all holding rifles, posed standing and sitting in front of an adobe building with two dogs, 1881-1884 (Box 2)
    Transcription of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Ausflug von Soldanten in Neutria auf der Jadg
    English translation of the deutscher Schrift inscription: Excursion by Soldiers in hunting gear in eutria